Guide to the Boris Kaufman Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Boris Kaufman papers
1836-2004
GEN MSS 562
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
13.74
(25 boxes) + 1 record album storage
The Boris Kaufman Papers contain professional papers, correspondence, writings, and other material documenting the life and work of cinematographer Boris Kaufman, as well as film production and cinematographic practice in France and the United States during the middle decades of the 20th century.
Kaufman, Boris
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Boris Kaufman Papers were acquired through purchase from André Kaufman on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2005. fund, 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 20-21, 24-25 and 26 (Record album storage): Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
BORIS KAUFMAN (1906-1980)
Boris Kaufman, a cinematographer, was born and raised in Bialystok, in the northeastern part of modern-day Poland and, following WWI, educated and trained in France. He is well known for his work with Jean Vigo in France from the late 1920s to the mid 1930s and for his work with Elia Kazan and Sidney Lumet in the U.S. in the 1950s and 1960s; Kazan's On the Waterfront (1954) won an Academy Award for best black-and-white cinematography. Kaufman was the youngest of three brothers, including filmmaker Denis Kaufman (who adopted the name Dziga Vertov) and cinematographer Mikhail Kaufman. Further information is available in standard print and online biographical resources.
The following chronology provides dates for key events and film projects:
1906 August 24 Boris Kaufman born in Bialystok, modern-day Poland
1927 Les Halles Centrales
1930 A propos de Nice
1933 Zéro de conduite
1934 L'Atalante
1936 On ne roule pas Antoinette
1938 Fort Dolorès
1939 Sérénade
1939-41 serves in French infantry
1941-42 moves to New York
1942-43 works for National Film Board of Canada
1943-45 works for U.S. Office of War Information
1945 A Better Tomorrow
1954 Garden of Eden
1954 On the Waterfront
1954 Within Man's Power
1956 Baby Doll
1956 Crowded Paradise
1956 Patterns
1956 Twelve Angry Men
1959 That Kind of Woman
1959 The Fugitive Kind
1961 Splendor in the Grass
1962 Long Day's Journey into Night
1963 All the Way Home
1964 The Pawnbroker
1964 The World of Henry Orient
1965 Film
1966 The Group
1967 Bye Bye Braverman
1968 Uptight
1968 The Brotherhood
1969 Tell Me that You Love Me, Junie Moon
1972 retires from filmmaking
1980 June 24 Boris Kaufman dies in New York
Scope and Contents
The Boris Kaufman Papers contain professional papers, correspondence, writings, and other material documenting the life and work of cinematographer Boris Kaufman, as well as film production and cinematographic practice during the middle decades of the 20th century. Kaufman, educated and trained in Paris before moving to the United States in the early 1940s, is well known for his collaborations with the filmmakers Jean Vigo, Elia Kazan, and Sidney Lumet, among others, and was awarded an Academy Award for his work on Kazan's On the Waterfront (1954) in the category of black-and-white cinematography. The collection spans the years 1836 to 2004, with the bulk of the collection dating from the 1930s through 1970s.
The collection is housed in 25 boxes and organized into four series: Professional Papers, Correspondence, Writings, and Other Material. Boxes 21-23 contain Oversize material and boxes 24 and 25 contain Restricted Fragile Papers and Restricted Fragile Oversize respectively.
Series I, Professional Papers, housed in boxes 1-11, contains material relating to films on which Kaufman worked, including clippings, printed ephemera, contracts, correspondence, photographs, cut film and negatives, shooting scripts, manuscript notes, and crew and staff lists. Papers are arranged alphabetically first by title of film and then by type of material. Materials date from Les Halles Centrales (1927) to Tell Me that You Love Me, Junie Moon (1969).
The Professional Papers series features hundreds of stills and publicity (studio) photographs for several films, including L'Atalante, Baby Doll, The Fugitive Kind, On the Waterfront, That Kind of Woman, and Twelve Angry Men. There are photographs of Kaufman, directors, including Elia Kazan and Sidney Lumet, and actors and actresses, including Jean Daste, Dita Parlo, Marlon Brando, Sophia Loren, Henry Fonda, Eli Wallach, and Karl Malden, as well as other cast and crew members.
In addition to the photographs, shooting scripts for numerous films, including Baby Doll, The Brotherhood, The Fugitive Kind, Long Day's Journey into Night, On the Waterfront, and Splendor in the Grass are annotated with manuscript notes and diagrams on how to shoot particular scenes.
A small amount of correspondence has been maintained in the professional files. There are letters regarding production and fan mail. Cross-references have been provided to established headings in the Correspondence series when appropriate. The clippings and printed ephemera consist chiefly of reviews and publicity for films.
Series II, Correspondence, housed in boxes 12-15, is organized into four subseries: Boris Kaufman Correspondence, Helen Kaufman Correspondence, André Kaufman Correspondence, and Third Party Correspondence.
The Boris Kaufman Correspondence consists chiefly of single and small groups of incoming letters from production companies, colleagues in the film industry, film scholars, writers, and family; there are some carbons and holograph drafts of outgoing letters. Correspondents include: Claude Aveline, Dian Dincin Buchman, Jules Dassin, Abel Gance, Elia Kazan, Stanley Kubrick, Jean Lods, Sidney Lumet, Pierre Merle, Jean Painlevé, Otto Preminger, Claude Renoir, Jean Renoir, and Jean and Luce Vigo. Letters from filmmakers show the respect Kaufman enjoyed among professional members of the film community. Letters are chiefly in English and French, with some in Russian.
Helen Kaufman Correspondence, housed in box 14, consists of letters to Helen Kaufman, Boris Kaufman's wife. There are letters from family members, friends, and colleagues of her husband, including condolence letters following his death. Most letters date from 1980 to 1982. Noteworthy correspondents include Elia Kazan and Sidney Lumet. Letters are chiefly in English and French, with some in Russian.
André Kaufman Correspondence, housed in box 15, contains letters to André Kaufman, Boris and Helen's son. There are letters dating from 1983 to 2004 from Dian Dincin Buchman, Elia Kazan, John Mackay, and others.
The small group of Third Party Correspondence, housed in box 15, consists of all loose third party correspondence. The bulk of these letters probably came to Kaufman as enclosures and, over time, were separated from the original letters. The subseries includes introduction letters on Kaufman's behalf, all dating February 10, 1942, from Benedict Gimbel to broadcasting companies.
Series III, Writings, housed in box 16, is organized into two subseries: Writings of Boris Kaufman and Writings of Others.
Kaufman's writings include corrected drafts and printed versions for several articles and lectures. Among the writings are corrected holograph and typescript drafts, galley proofs, and a reprint for a 1959 article on cinematography entitled "Film Making as an Art." There are also reports submitted [to the Princeton Film Center?] on three photographic devices or techniques (the pictoscope, pictograph, and magigraph) and reflections on working with the filmmakers Jean Vigo and Elia Kazan.
The Writings of Others subseries includes articles relating to Kaufman or colleagues and articles written by Kaufman family members and colleagues. There is a biographical essay on Kaufman by Cecile Starr and interviews with Kaufman by Donald Crafton, Simon Kagan, and Jonas Mekas. In addition, there is a printed interview with Kaufman's brother Mikhail discussing production of The Man with a Movie Camera (1929), and a printed article, "The Factory of Facts and Other Writings," by his brother Dziga Vertov.
Series IV, Other Material, housed in boxes 17-20, is organized into five subseries: Artwork, Helen Kaufman Papers, Photographs, Printed Ephemera, and Other. The papers include manuscript notes, in French and Russian, dating from the Jean Vigo years.
Oversize, housed in boxes 21-23, contains material from Series I, III and IV. Restricted Fragile Papers and Restricted Fragile Oversize are housed in boxes 24 and 25 respectively.
Cinematography; Motion pictures -- Production and direction; Motion pictures -- France; Motion pictures -- United States; Audiovisual materials; Film scripts; Photographic prints; Cinematographers; Aveline, Claude, 1901-1992; Brando, Marlon, 1924-2004; Dassin, Jules, 1911-2008; Dasté, Jean, 1904-1994; Fonda, Henry, 1905-1982; Gance, Abel, 1889-1981; Kaufman, Boris; Kaufman, Mikhail Abramovich, 1897-1980; Kazan, Elia, 1909-2003; Kubrick, Stanley, 1928-1999; Lods, Jean; Loren, Sophia, 1934-; Lumet, Sidney, 1924-2011; Malden, Karl, 1912-2009; Merle, Pierre; Painlevé, Jean; Parlo, Dita; Preminger, Otto, 1906-1986; Renoir, Jean, 1894-1979; Vertov, Dziga, 1896-1954; Vigo, Jean, 1905-1934; Wallach, Eli, 1915-2014
- Professional Papers, 1927-1980; Series I; 4.38; (11 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Professional Papers, is arranged alphabetically first by film or project title, then by type of material.
  A Propos de Nice
  - Clippings, 1976 Feb 14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - All the Way Home
    - Clippings, 1962-63, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - L'Atalante
    - Clippings, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Photographs, [ca. 1934]
    - Printed ephemera, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Baby Doll
    - Clippings, 1956-57 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Clippings removed from binder, 1956-57 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Contract, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1957 Feb 19 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Correspondence, Box 12, folder 174
    - Notes, 1957, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Film boards, [ca. 1956-57]
      Contain cut film negatives and prints.
    - Photographs, [1956] (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
      Includes photographs by Floyd McCarthy, Warner Brothers
    - Photographs removed from binder, [1956] (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
      Includes photographs by Floyd McCarty and Mac Julian, Warner Brothers
    - Printed ephemera, 1956-57 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Shooting script, typescript mimeograph, annotated and bound with list of shots and notes, [1956] (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - A Better Tomorrow
    - Photographs, [ca. 1945] (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - The Brotherhood
    Note: The cut film in boxes 3-4 is stored separately in cold storage.
    - Blueprints and drawings, 1967 (Box bsd, Folder 20)
    - Clippings, 1967 Nov 12 (Box bsd, Folder 21)
    - Cut film, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 22-29)
    - Cut film, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 30-37)
    - Cut film, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 38-45)
    - Cut film, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Cut film, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 47-54)
    - Cut film, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 55-62)
    - Cut film, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 63-67)
    - Photographs, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 68)
      Includes photographs by "Muky"
    - Shooting script, typescript mimeograph, annotated, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 69)
    - Staff list, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 70)
    - Storyboard for "First Floor Set", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Bye Bye Braverman
    - Contract, 1967-68 (Box 5, Folder 72)
    - Correspondence, 1967-68 (Box 5, Folder 73)
    - Personnel list, 1967 Apr 6 (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - Shooting script, typescript mimeograph, annotated, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Crowded Paradise
    - Clippings, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Printed ephemera, 1956 May (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Film
    - Clippings, 1964-65 (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Film script, "Untitled Film Script" by Samuel Beckett, typescript mimeograph, 1963 May (Box 5, Folder 79)
      Includes scripts for "The Hard Boiled Egg" by Eugene Ionesco and "The Compartment" by Harold Pinter
    - Notes, [ca. 1964] (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Publicity, 1965-66 (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Fort Dolorès
    - Clippings, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - The Fugitive Kind
    - Clippings, 1959-61 (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 84)
      See also: Correspondence, American Cinematographer, Box 12, folder 173
    - Notes, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - Photographs removed from binder (Box 6, Folder 86-88)
    - Printed ephemera, n.y. Apr 13 (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - Shooting script, Final draft, typescript mimeograph, annotated and bound with location shooting schedule and personnel list, 1959 Jun 1 (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - Garden of Eden
    - Clippings, 1957 Dec 18 (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - The Group
    - Clippings, 1965-66 (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - Correspondence, 1965 Nov 5 (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - Schedules and lists, 1965, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 94)
    - Shooting script, typescript mimeograph, annotated, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - Les Halles Centrales
    - Photographs, 1927 (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - Long Day's Journey into Night
    - Clippings and printed ephemera, 1961-64 (Box 7, Folder 97)
    - Correspondence, 1961, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 98)
      See also: The Fugitive Kind, Box 6, folder 84 and Correspondence, American Cinematographer, Box 12, folder 173
    - Notes, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 99)
    - Photographs, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 100)
    - Shooting script, typescript mimeograph, annotated, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 101)
    - Staff and crew list (Box 7, Folder 102)
  - On ne roule pas Antionette
    - Clippings, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 103)
  - On the Waterfront
    - Call sheets, 1953, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 104)
    - Clippings, 1953-80, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 105-107)
    - Clippings removed from binder, 1953-55 (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - Correspondence, 1953-55, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 109)
    - Crew sheet, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 110)
    - Notes, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 111)
    - Photographs, 1954-55, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 112-113)
    - Photographs, 1954-55, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 114-115)
    - Photographs removed from binder, 1954, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 116-117)
    - Shooting script, typescript mimeograph, annotated and bound with notes and shooting schedule (Box 8, Folder 118)
    - Untitled list, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 119)
  - Patterns
    - Clippings, 1955-56 (Box 8, Folder 120)
    - Photographs, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 121)
  - The Pawnbroker
    - Call and location sheets, 1963, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 122)
    - Clippings, 1963, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 123)
    - Contract, 1963 Sep 30 (Box 8, Folder 124)
    - Correspondence, 1965, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 125)
    - Photographs, n.d.
      Photographs by "Muky"
    - Printed ephemera, [1964?] (Box 8, Folder 126)
    - Shooting script, typescript mimeograph, annotated, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 127)
  - Sérénade
    - Clippings and printed ephemera (Box 9, Folder 128)
    - Photographs, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 129)
  - Splendor in the Grass
    - Clippings, 1960-61, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 130)
    - Correspondence, 1960-62 (Box 9, Folder 131)
    - Notes removed from shooting script, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 132)
    - Printed ephemera, 1961 Nov (Box 9, Folder 133)
    - Shooting script, typescript mimeograph, annotated and bound, 1960 Mar 17 (Box 9, Folder 134)
  - Tell Me that You Love Me, Junie Moon
    - Clippings, 1969-70 (Box 9, Folder 135)
      Includes photocopies
    - Contract, 1969 Jun 10 (Box 9, Folder 136)
    - Notebook, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 137)
    - Printed publicity, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 138)
    - Shooting script, typescript [mimeograph?], 1969 May 1 (Box 9, Folder 139)
    - Staff and crew sheet (Box 10, Folder 140)
  - That Kind of Woman
    - Clippings, 1959, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 141)
    - Diagrams, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 142)
    - Photographs, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 143-146)
      Includes photographs by A. Bagley
    - Shooting script, "Final White Script," typescript mimeograph, annotated and bound with shooting schedule, 1958 Jun 12 (Box 10, Folder 147)
  - Twelve Angry Men
    - Clippings, 1956-57 (Box 10, Folder 148)
    - Clippings removed from binder, 1956-58 (Box 10, Folder 149)
    - Correspondence, 1956 May 16 (Box 10, Folder 150)
    - Cut film, n.d. (Box cs, Folder 151)
    - Photographs removed from binder, 1956, n.d. (Box cs, Folder 152)
    - Shooting script, typescript mimeograph, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 153)
  - Uptight
    - Clippings, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 154)
    - Contract, 1968 Jul 1 (Box 11, Folder 155)
    - Correspondence, 1968-69 (Box 11, Folder 156)
      Includes letters to Kaufman from Jules Dassin
    - "First Pilot Lightings" sheets, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 157)
  - Within Man's Power
    - Clippings, 1954 Jun (Box 11, Folder 158)
  - The World of Henry Orient
    - Cast call sheet, 1963 Sep 9 (Box 11, Folder 159)
    - Clippings, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 160)
    - Notes, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 161)
    - Photographs, 1968, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 162)
      Includes photographs by "Muky" and Frank D. Dandridge
    - Press release, n.y. Aug 5 (Box 11, Folder 163)
    - Shooting script, "First Revise," typescript mimeograph, annotated, 1963 May (Box 11, Folder 164)
    - Staff and crew list (Box 11, Folder 165)
  - Zéro de conduite
    - Clippings, 1962, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 166)
    - Printed ephemera, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 167)
      See also: L'Atalante, Box 1, folder 4
- Correspondence, 1932-2004; Series II; 1.46; (4 boxes)
  Series II, Correspondence, is organized into four subseries: Boris Kaufman Correspondence, Helen Kaufman Correspondence, André Kaufman Correspondence, and Third Party Correspondence.
  - BORIS KAUFMAN CORRESPONDENCE
    - "A" General, 1954 Apr 28 (Box 12, Folder 168)
    - Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences, 1954-72 (Box 12, Folder 169)
    - Affiliated Film Producers, Inc., 1947, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 170)
    - Almendros, Nestor, 1978 Dec 19 (Box 12, Folder 171)
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1979 May 9 (Box 12, Folder 172)
    - American Cinematographer, 1955 Mar 23 (Box 12, Folder 173)
      See also: Professional Papers, The Fugitive Kind, Box 6, folder 84 and Long Day's Journey into Night, Box 7, folder 98
    - American Society of Cinematographers, 1954-79 (Box 12, Folder 174)
      See also: Professional Papers, Baby Doll, Correspondence, Box 1, folder 9
    - Artforum, 1972-76 (Box 12, Folder 175)
      Includes negatives
    - Astra-Paris-Films, 1947 Jun (Box 12, Folder 176)
    - Aveline, Claude, 1947-55, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 177)
    - "B" General, 1941-59 (Box 12, Folder 178)
    - Bac, A[ndré?], 1959 May 24 (Box 12, Folder 179)
    - Barnouw, Erik, 1972 Oct 8 (Box 12, Folder 180)
    - Bazin, Janine, 1964 Jun 8 (Box 12, Folder 181)
    - Belgatos, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 182)
    - Ben-Anat, Gera (cousin), 1967-80 (Box 12, Folder 183)
    - Ben-Anat, [Malki?], 1975-76 (Box 12, Folder 184)
    - Berger, Ludwig, 1960 Sep 11 (Box 12, Folder 185)
    - Beveridge, James A., 1975, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 186)
    - Blum, Dora, 1951-66, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 187)
    - British Film Institute, 1964 (Box 12, Folder 188)
    - Buchman, Dian Dincin, 1955 Mar 31 (Box 12, Folder 189)
    - "C" General, 1935-57 (Box 12, Folder 190)
    - Canadian Society of Cinematographers, 1963, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 191)
    - Chermayeff, Barbara, 1977 Jan 25 (Box 12, Folder 192)
    - Cinémathèque québécoise, 1969 May 9 (Box 12, Folder 193)
    - Columbia University, 1980 Apr 25 (Box 12, Folder 194)
    - Consolidated Film Industries, Inc., 1960 May 26 (Box 12, Folder 195)
    - Cowan, Lester
      See: Professional Papers, On the Waterfront, Correspondence, Box 7, folder 109
    - Crafton, Donald, 1977-78 (Box 12, Folder 196)
    - "D" General, 1938, 1964 (Box 12, Folder 197)
    - Daedalus, 1958-66, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 198)
    - Dassin, Jules
      See: Professional Papers, Uptight, Correspondence, Box 11, folder 156
    - "E" General, 1954 Feb 17 (Box 12, Folder 199)
    - E. I. du Pont de Nemours & Company, 1961 Sep 12 (Box 12, Folder 200)
    - "F" General, 1934-73, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 201)
    - Falkenberg, Paul, 1948 Oct 22 (Box 12, Folder 202)
    - Famartists Productions
      See: Professional Papers, The Group, Correspondence, Box 6, folder 93
    - Fitelson, H. William, 1946 Apr 8 (Box 12, Folder 203)
    - Flaherty, Robert J[oseph?], 1948 Jan 9 (Box 12, Folder 204)
    - Freeman, Benjamin H., 1941-43 (Box 12, Folder 205-206)
    - "G" General, 1948, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 207)
    - Gance, Abel, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 208)
    - Gaumont-Franco-Film-Aubert, 1932 (Box 12, Folder 209)
    - Gladiator Films, 1938 Jul 12 (Box 12, Folder 210)
    - Gomes, Paulo Emîlio Salles, 1950-62, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 211)
    - Grove Press, 1968 Jan 21 (Box 12, Folder 212)
      Includes carbon of letter from Grove Press to Luce Vigo
    - "H" General, 1947, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 213)
    - Halpern-[Pruginin?], "Masha" (aunt), 1964-80, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 214)
    - Hammid, Olya, 1960, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 215)
    - HIAS-JCA Emigration Association, 1941, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 216)
    - Hubley, Faith, 1968 Feb 11 (Box 13, Folder 217)
    - International Photographers of the Motion Picture Industry, 1948-75 (Box 13, Folder 218)
      See also: Other Material, Photographs, Box 17, folders 356-357
    - "J" General, 1941 May 6 (Box 13, Folder 219)
    - Jaffe Agency, Inc., 1954-55 (Box 13, Folder 220)
    - Johnson, Anna, 1970, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 221)
    - "K" General, 1950-79 (Box 13, Folder 222)
    - Kaufman, André (son) (Box 13, Folder 223)
    - Kaufman, Helen (wife), 1946-50 (Box 13, Folder 224-225)
    - Kaufman, Mikhail, 1945-77, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 226)
      Includes translations of letters from Russian to English in unidentified hand
    - Kazan, Elia, 1953-70, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 227)
    - Kepes, Gyorgy
      See: Daedalus, Box 12, folder 198
    - Kepes, Juliet, 1976-79, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 228)
    - Kubrick, Stanley, 1962 May (Box 13, Folder 229)
    - "L" General, 1941-63 (Box 13, Folder 230)
    - Lods, Jean, 1966-71 (Box 13, Folder 231)
    - Lumet, Sidney, 1957-69, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 232)
    - "M" General, 1939-61 (Box 13, Folder 233)
    - Merle, Pierre, 1957, 1959 (Box 13, Folder 234)
    - Michaud, Michael, 1975 Aug 25 (Box 13, Folder 235)
    - Michelson, Annette
      See: Artforum, Box 12, folder 175
    - Mills, Brian, 1969-81, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 236)
    - Mitra, Subrata, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 237)
    - Motion Picture Association of America, 1964 Jun 19 (Box 13, Folder 238)
    - Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.). Film Library, 1936-74 (Box 13, Folder 239)
    - National Broadcasting Company, Inc., 1955 Apr 14 (Box 13, Folder 240)
    - National Film Board of Canada, 1942-49, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 241)
    - National Refugee Service (U.S.), 1941 Mar 20 (Box 13, Folder 242)
    - New York Public Library, 1974 Oct 21 (Box 13, Folder 243)
    - Northwestern University, 1975 Mar 26 (Box 13, Folder 244)
    - "P" General, 1936-66 (Box 13, Folder 245)
    - Painlevé, Jean, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 246)
    - Positif, 1964 Oct 2 (Box 13, Folder 247)
    - Preminger, Otto, 1957 Jun (Box 13, Folder 248)
    - Pressburger, Fred
    - Princeton Film Center, Inc., 1950-52 (Box 13, Folder 249)
    - Pruginin, Lilit, 1971-78 (Box 13, Folder 250)
    - Pruginin, Yosef, 1976, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 251)
    - "R" General, 1941-69, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 252)
    - Renoir, Claude, 1947-49 (Box 13, Folder 253)
    - Renoir, Jean, 1938 Apr 7 (Box 13, Folder 254)
    - Robbins, Leroy, 1945-75 (Box 13, Folder 255)
      Includes photographs
    - [Rodakiewicz?], Henwar, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 256)
    - Roemer, Michael, 1962 Dec 17 (Box 13, Folder 257)
    - "S" General, 1938-80 (Box 13, Folder 258)
    - Saudek, Robert, 1966 Aug 26 (Box 13, Folder 259)
    - Sharples, Winston, 1975 Mar 12 (Box 13, Folder 260)
    - Smith College, 1960 (Box 13, Folder 261)